i've seen plenty of content from health
influencers claiming that their diet is
the one that reverses the plaque buildup
in our arteries but I haven't seen any
point out a fascinating study on the
Mediterranean diet and the results
indicating profound benefit including
reversing
atherosclerosis in this study called the
Cardoprev study the researchers examined
the impact two different diets had on
reducing cardiovascular events like
stroke heart attacks and so on in
addition the researchers measured the
amount of plaque buildup in the
participants arteries so we'll discuss
both the two diets that people were
randomly allocated to were the uh
Mediterranean diet as if that wasn't
obvious and the low-fat diet i'll list a
few of the details for each diet on the
screen for you now both groups of
participants at baseline were the same
across a list of measurements and both
groups were on each diet for 7 years
during that seven years researchers did
further measurements and checks
especially at the 5-year mark as we'll
see now before we get to the results I
should point out that this is a
secondary prevention trial which means
that all the participants had coronary
heart disease diagnosed so a high-risk
population so when measuring the plaque
in the arteries the researchers measured
at baseline five years and seven years
check this out the black line is the
Mediterranean diet and the gray one is
the low-fat diet if the lines go down
that indicates reduced plaque in the
arteries and I probably don't need to
spell it out for you but the
Mediterranean diet showed significant
improvement at least in the first 5
years now interestingly the low-fat diet
did not show any improvement although in
defense of the low-fat diet it also
didn't show any notable worsening either
like the plaque was stopped in its
tracks okay remarkable and exactly why I
wanted to bring this study to your
attention but you know what else is
remarkable if we pop open the
supplemental data don't worry this will
be easy to read the top line is the
amount of calories consumed so notice
how at baseline both groups were
consuming the same amount yet at 5 years
and 7 years the low-fat diet was in a
greater caloric deficit than the
Mediterranean diet so in spite of more
than double the calorie deficit the
low-fat diet underperformed compared to
the Mediterranean diet one more thing I
should point out uh there was slightly
worse compliance or uh stick tuitiveness
with the low-fat diet so that may
contribute to some of the results here
especially since those that were on the
Mediterranean diet were more compliant
and improved their compliance but even
so what we're most concerned about isn't
if we see reversal of plaque i mean
don't get me wrong that's impressive but
what we actually want is cardiovascular
disease events so do we see a reduction
do people experience fewer heart attacks
for example well we'll get to that next
but if you want a deeper analysis of
this study including a full written
research review of the study with
applicable takeaways it's included with
the Physionic Insiders the uh link to
join along with access to all my work
including live sessions with yours truly
here is in the description box i hope to
see you there well if we crack open the
data you'll note the blue line is the
low-fat diet and the red line is the
Mediterranean diet in addition you'll
notice the seven years of the trial on
the horizontal axis and the
cardiovascular disease incidents on the
vertical if the lines go up that
indicates more cardiovascular events so
clearly considering there's a massive
white space between the two diets the
Mediterranean diet outperformed the
low-fat diet in this metric too and you
can imagine some of that is likely due
to plaque regression but how is the
Mediterranean diet accomplishing these
benefits in this high-risisk population
people with established heart disease
well the researchers speculate that
because the Mediterranean diet increases
HDL that's a high density lipoprotein
particles that can remove cholesterol
out of the atheroma so the plaque
buildup this process is called reverse
cholesterol transport back to the liver
for excretion in addition it's possible
that the Mediterranean diet reduces
inflammatory molecules that might
encourage endothelial injury so these
key cells that regulate blood flow and
blood pressure in fact while this study
clearly shows long-term Mediterranean
diet improves heart disease
significantly for people with
established heart disease that last
mechanism has been shown in some other
studies before especially in relation to
a key oil used in the Mediterranean diet
olive oil and yet a prominent physician
and scientist says olive oil and the
Mediterranean diet cause heart disease
no not joking literally causes heart
disease in complete opposition of what
we just went over why let's find out
together in this next video